We have a player ship, weapons
我们已经做好了玩家飞船,武器
and hazard objects.
小行星灾难
We need to bring them together in to a
我们得把它们重组到一起
simple but playable game.
让它们赤尾一个简单可玩的游戏
To do this we need to create a
为了这个目的我们需要
game controller to run our game,
建立一个游戏控制器
to spawn our hazards,
生成我们一波波的小行星
keep track of and display our score
记录并显示得分
and when our player is destroyed end our game.
当玩家飞船被毁就结束游戏
First create a new game object
首先建立一个新的对象
to hold our game controller logic.
来保存我们游戏控制器的逻辑
Rename this game object Game Controller.
把这个对象命名为Game Controller
And then reset the transform.
重置一下它的变形组件
For this game object this step isn't
对于当前这个游戏而言
absolutely necessary as this game object
重置这个步骤并不是必须的
will not have a physical presence in our game.
游戏控制器这个对象并不会出现在游戏场景中
It won't have a collider and it won't be rendered.
它没有碰撞检测机也不需要渲染
That being said it is always best
我们提到过最好是把所有的对象
to keep everything in our project neat and tidy
都弄的整齐紧凑
and there is no good reason not to put
所以我们并没有什么好理由
the game controller cleanly at origin.
不把游戏控制器放在原点
Using the Tag drop-down menu in the header
在 Game Controller标题栏下的标签下拉菜单中
of the Game Controller game object select the
选择已有的标签
pre-made tag GameController.
GameController
With our game object setup
我们的对象已经设置好了
let's write our logic.
下面我们来设定一下逻辑
With the Game Controller selected
在Game Controller对象选定的情况下
use the Add Component button
点击Add Component按钮
to create a new script
新建一个脚本
named GameController.
命名为GameController
Accept the changes to add this new script
确认更改
to GameController.
并新增这个脚本
Select Assets and file the GameController script
点选资源文件夹
in the Scripts folder.
把GameController脚本文件移到Scripts文件夹中
Open the Scripts folder
打开Scripts文件夹
and open the GameController script for editing.
打开编辑GameController脚本
Our game controller will perform
我们的控制器
several different tasks.
主要完成一下几个任务
The primary task however will be
首要任务是产生
spawning the hazards in our game.
游戏中的小行星灾难
So the first thing we will need in this script
所以这个脚本要做的第一件事是
is a public GameObject reference to our hazard.
建立一个公有的对小行星对象的引用
Next we need to do something
之后我们需要对小行星
with these hazards.
执行一些操作
We need to spawn them, preferably in waves
我们需要产生小行星
for our player to fight through.
最好是产生一波波的小行星让玩家射击
Let's write a new function to spawn
让我们写一些能产生小行星
our waves of hazards.
的方法
Write void SpawnWaves.
敲入代码void SpawnWaves
Now we need to call this function.
现在我们需要调用这个代码
There are some functions that are called
有些方法Unity会
automatically by Unity
自动调用
but most of the functions that we write
但是大多数我们自己编写的方法
we will need to call ourselves
都需要我们自己调用
or they won't be executed.
否则代码不会被执行
We want our SpawnWaves function to
我们希望SpawnWaves这个函数
work for most of the duration of our game.
在大部分时间都被调用
So let's call SpawnWaves from start.
所以我们在start中调用SpawnWaves
So let's write void Start.
让我们写下代码void Start
Unity will call Start on the very first frame
Unity会在游戏开始的时候
that this game object is enabled
调用Start方法
and then Start will call SpawnWaves.
之后Start会调用SpawnWaves
What do we want SpawnWaves to do?
我们需要SpawnWaves执行那些操作?
We want SpawnWaves to instantiate our hazards.
我们需要SpawnWaves初始化我们小行星灾难
We want to instantiate our hazards
我们需要在某个小行星出生点的位置
at a spawnPosition
产生一些小行星
with a spawnRotation applied.
这些小行星要按照给出的spawnRotation旋转
We have 3 parameters for instantiate
这里我们有三个参数
and we need a value for each of them.
我们需要给这三个参数赋值
Let's look at each of these parameters
所以让我们逐个看看
1 parameter at a time.
这些参数
Our object Hazard has already been defined
我们的小行星对象已经被
as a public variable.
定义成了公有的参数
Our spawnPosition is a vector3 value
我们的spawnPosition参数是一个vector3的值
so let's create a vector3 variable called
所以我们建立一个vector3的变量
spawnPosition, which we will set to
叫做spawnPosition
a new vector3.
把一个新建的vector3赋值给spawnPosition
Our spawnRotation is a quaternion value.
我们的spawnRotation是一个四元变量
So let's create a quaternion variable
让我们新建一个四元的变量
called spawnRotation
命名为spawnRotation
which we will set to a new quaternion.
把一个新建的四元变量赋值给它
Both of these will change before we're done.
spawnPosition和spawnRotation的值我们稍后会做调整
Let's look at how we can assign
让我们先看看如何
working values to these.
给这些参数赋值
Hazard is a public variable.
Hazard是一个公有参数
We can set this directly in the Inspector.
这个参数我们可以在Inspector中直接设置
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
We can see the hazard property
我们在GameController这个组件上可以看到
on the GameController component.
hazard这个属性
In the Prefabs folder we can find our
在Prefabs文件夹中
Asteroid prefab.
我们找到小行星的预制件
Drag the Asteroid prefab on to the
把小行星的预制件
Game Controller component and drop it
拖拽到Game Controller组件
on to the Hazard slot to create the reference.
把预制件放置到Hazard槽位
We want to be able to set our spawn position
我们需要在编辑器中
in the Editor as well.
设置我们的小行星产生位置
Return to our GameController script.
回到我们的GameController脚本
For our spawnPosition
对于spawnPosition这个参数
let's define a public vector3
我们定义一个公有的vector3参数
variable called spawnValues.
命名为spawnValues
Why can't we just use spawnPosition here?
我们这里为什么不直接使用spawnPosition呢?
We will see why in just a moment.
我们等会就知道为什么了
Patience.
耐心点
Save this script and let's set
保存脚本
spawnValue in Unity.
让我们在Unity中设置一下spawnValue
To help visualise this let's drag and asteroid
为了让我们更好的理解
prefab in to the scene temporarily.
我们暂时先把一个小行星拖拽到场景中
So on what position along the Y axis
小行星产生的位置
do we want to spawn our hazards?
在Y轴上应该为多少呢?
On the X/Z plane or the game plane?
在X/Z平面和游戏平面?
So 0 on the Y axis.
所以Y值应该为0
What about the position on the X/Z plane?
在X/Z平面上的位置又如何呢
This could be better seen
我们可以通过游戏场景相机观察
through the Game View camera.
这样会更清晰
What position on the Z axis?
Z轴的值应该是多少?
Up, out of the game area.
向上,直到游戏场景以外
That looks like about 16.
看起来16差不多
So let's set the spawnValue Z to 16.
我们把spawnValue的Z值设置为16
Now what about the X axis
X方向的参数又该如何设置
Well we can't really use a single value here.
我们这里不要使用一个固定值
If we did we will define a
如果我们这样做了
single point for our spawnPosition,
我们会只产生一个固定的spawnPosition
and for that we could have used a simple
我们可以向子弹的产生点那样
game object's transform, like we did for
使用一个对象的变形组建
the shotSpawn on the player ship.
使小行星的生成位置可以发生变化
What we really want here is a random
我们这里需要的是一个
point in the X axis.
随机的X值
One that is a new random value for
这个值可以让每个小行星
each new hazard we spawn.
都在不同的位置产生出来
This is why we couldn't use spawnPosition directly.
这就是我们为什么不直接使用spawnPosition的原因
Let's return to our script
让我们回到脚本继续编辑
We will use our spawnValues to set
我们用spawnValues来设定
a random spawnPosition.
一个随机的spawnPosition
Our spawnPosition is made up of
spawnPosition是由
X, Y and Z values.
X, Y and Z三个值组成
Working from back to front
从最后一个参数依次向前赋值
our spawnPosition Z will be our
spawnPosition的Z值是
spawnValues Z, or outside the
spawnValues的Z值
top of the game area.
这个值要在游戏区域上方之外
Our spawnPosition Y will be
spawnPosition的Y值就是
our spawnValue Y
spawnValue的Y值
or 0 on the game plane.
这个值是0也就是在游戏所在的平面
Our spawnPosition X is the one
spawnPosition的X值
that's more tricky.
非常有技巧
We can't use a single value here.
这里没法用一个值表示
We will use our spawnValue X
我们用spawnValue的X值
to control a random value.
来控制这个随机值
Let's search the documentation for random again
让我们再在文档中搜索一下random
so we can look at the Random class.
我们可以看看Random这个类
In this case we want to look at
这里我们看
Random.Range.
Random.Range
We give Random.Range a min and a max value
我们给Random.Range一个最大和一个最小值
and randomRange will return
这个函数会随机返回
a random value between those 2 values.
最大值和最小值之间的一个值
This means we can feed Random.Range
这意味着我们可以把
with the values of the edges of our game area
游戏边界的值给Random.Range
and it will return a random value between them.
Random.Range会返回一个边界之间的随机数
Copy Random.Range and return to our script.
复制Random.Range
Paste Random.Range in to our code
粘贴到我们的脚本中
and let's feed Random.Range with
给Random.Range赋值
- spawnValues.x
and spawnValues.x.
和spawnValues.x
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
Where are the edges of our game?
我们游戏的边界是多少?
Let's move our asteroid along the X axis.
让我们把小行星沿着X轴移动一下
And it looks like about -6 and 6.
差不多是-6到6
So spawnValues.x is 6.
所以spawnValues.x的值是6
Lastly we need to set our spawnRotation.
最后我们需要设定spawnRotation
Back to our GameController script
返回我们的GameController脚本
let's find out more about
让我们在文档中
quaternion in the documentation.
找一下四元数的信息
Quaternions are complex.
四元数很复杂
We almost never access or modify
我们几乎无法直接获得
a quaternion directly.
或者更改一个四元数
There are many quaternion functions for us
这里有很多的四元数函数
for us to use.
可供我们使用
We won't be using any of the quaternion
我们并不会用到某个具体的
functions exactly, but we will be looking at
四元数方程
a quaternion property called Identity.
但是我们需要看一个四元数的叫Identity的属性
Quaternion.Identity corresponds with
Quaternion.Identity对应
no rotation of the quaternion.
一个非旋转的四元数
We will instantiate our hazards with
我们的小行星将被实例化
no rotation at all.
为没有任何翻转
Copy Quaternion.Identity
复制Quaternion.Identity
and return to our script.
回到我们的脚本
Paste this in to our code so the line reads
把它粘贴到我们的代码行中使代码成为
Quaternion spawnRotation = Quaternion.Identity.
Quaternion spawnRotation = Quaternion.Identity
Save this script and return to Unity to test.
保存脚本回到Unity测试一下
Remove our temporary asteroid.
把我们临时的那个小行星删除掉
Save the scene and play.
保存场景进入游戏模式
And we get a tumbling asteroid
我们得到了一个翻转的小行星
from a random point left to right
它产生的位置的左右距离是随机的
starting outside of the game area
它是从游戏场景上方发出的
and moving along the game plane.
并且它是沿着游戏平面飞行的
Let's enter and exit Play mode a few times.
让我们重新进入退出游戏模式重复几次
We can see that our spawn points are random
我们可以看到我们的小行星生成位置是随机的
and each new asteroid is spawned
所有小行星都在
at a new random location.
不同的位置生成
In the next assignment we will instantiate
下一个任务是
waves of hazards to challenge our player with.
生成一大波小行星来挑战我们的玩家